בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is נז *Nun Zayin*, we
continue in the אגדתא Agadata *Aggadeta* here some of the most essential
אגדתא Agadata *Aggadeta* about the חורבן הבית churban habayit. *Churban ha-Bayit*, and
we pick up at the bottom of נו עמוד ב *Nun Vav
amud bet*, and we are
just dealt with the whole issue about Titus and how he met
his downfall with a gnat. You know you have to sort of
acknowledge sort of the almost humor, the absurdity of like, you know,
we had Vespasian whose foot blew up and then Titus's gnat fell
into, you know, came up his nostril. So even though Vespasian is
sort of the good guy or somewhat in this story, you know,
it is very much like a bringing the mighty down, you know,
it is very much like an element of a little bit of
a mockery going on there. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and Titus
basically asked that God should not be able to judge him after
he died so that his ashes be spread over the seven seas.
And now we pick up four lines from the bottom on נו
עמוד ב *Nun Vav amud bet* and we have the following: אונקלוס
Onkelos בר bar קלוניקוס *Onkelos bar Kalonikos*, so Onkelos the son of
Kalonikos, בר bar אחתיה דטיטוס *bar achatei de-Titus* דהוה *de-hava*, he was
the, probably אונקלוס הגר *Onkelos
ha-Ger*, he was the son of the sister of Titus. בעא לגיורי
*ba'ei le-giurei* and he wanted to convert because eventually the story is
he's אונקלוס הגר *Onkelos ha-Ger*, he converts. So אזל azal, אסקיה לטיטוס
בנגידא *azal askei le-Titus be-negida*,
he brought Titus back up through some type of a witchcraft. אמר
ליה Amar lei *amar lei* and he said to him, so he
rose him from the dead and he said to him, מאן חשיב
בההוא עלמא *man chashiv be-hahu alma*, who is important in that world,
the world to come? אמר ליה Amar lei, *amar lei* he said
to him, ישראל Yisrael. *Yisrael*, the Jewish people, Israel. מה ma לי
li דבוקי בהו *ma lei devukei behu*, so should I therefore cleave
to them, should I join them in this world? אמר ליה Amar
lei *amar lei* מיליהו נפישן ולא velo מצית לקיומינהו *milaihu nefishan velo
matis le-kiyumaihu*, no,
their words are many, meaning, you know, it's very hard to be
a Jew, there's a lot of obligations, a lot of מצוות *mitzvot*.
You won't be able to fulfill it. זיל איגרי בהו בההוא עלמא
*zil igrei behu behahu alma*, look here's your best shot, so
attack them in this world and והוית רישא *havis reisha* and at
least you will be successful in this world in not in the
world to come, there, you know, you'll be punished, but at least
you might as well be successful in this world. דכתיב dechativ, *de-chtiv*
היו צריה לראש *hayu tzareha le-rosh*, its enemies were for a head.
כל המיצר לישראל נעשה ראש *kol ha-meitzar le-Yisrael na'aseh rosh*, anybody who
oppresses Israel, now the grammar here is because becomes a head, which
actually is, you know, becomes a leader, which actually is a little
depressing. It's like sort of an incentive for somebody to, you know,
oppress and afflict the Jews, you'll become a leader. So the commentary
say it means that you that only a great leader will oppress
Israel, you know, so it's sort of like will have already become
a leader, but it's not פשט pshat *peshat*, it's a way of
re-reading the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*.
We saw that with Vespasian,
yeah, but
it's actually not exact פשט *peshat* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. He
says you know what go ahead and attack them and afflict them
and that at least you'll be successful in this world. אמר ליה
amar leih, *amar lei* so he said, דיניה דההוא גברא במאי *dinei
de-hahu gavra be-mai*, so he wanted to know what would be the,
you know, what would be the consequence in the world to come.
So that man, meaning you, what's your punishment in the world to
come? That's what you did, you know, you attacked the Jewish people,
you destroyed the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis ha-Mikdash*. אמר amar, ליה
lei, *amar lei* במאי דפסק אנפשיה *be-mai de-pasak anafshei*, what I asked
for to be done to myself, that's what's done to me on
a daily basis. What does that mean? כל יומא מכנשי ליה lei,
לקטמיה *kol yoma machneshi lei le-katmei*, every day they my ashes are
regathered from the seven seas and presumably I'm like reconstituted in some
way. ודייני ליה lei *ve-dayni lei* and then I'm re-judged on a
daily basis. וקלו ליה *ve-kalu lei* and this is in the third
person, and they burn him, meaning I'm re-burned. ומבדרו אשבע ימי *ve-mabdru
a-shva yamei* and my ashes are spread over seven seas. So this
happens to me on a daily basis. So that's what will happen
to you, but you know, might as well have fun in this
world. אזל אסקיה לבלעם בנגידא *azal askei le-Bilam be-negida*, so then he
caused he brought Balaam back from the dead through witchcraft. אמר amar,
ליה *amar lei* he said to him, מאן חשיב בההוא עלמא *man
chashiv be-hahu alma*, who is important in that world, the world to
come? אמר amar ליה *amar lei* ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*, Israel. מה לי
li דבוקי בהו *ma lei devukei behu*, so should I cleave to
them? אמר amar ליה *amar lei* לא lo תדרוש שלומם וטובתם כל
הימים *lo tidrosh shelomam ve-tovatam kol ha-yamim*, no, don't seek after their
well-being. It might be their good in the world to come, but
you should hate them in this world. אמר amar ליה *amar lei*
דיניה דההוא גברא במאי *dinei de-hahu gavra be-mai*, how are you being
judged in that world, in the world, you know, in the world
to come? אמר amar, ליה *amar lei* בשכבת זרע רותחת *be-shichvat zera
rotachat*, in boiling semen. So that's two explanations given to that is
number one because he caused בני ישראל Yisrael, *Bnei Yisrael* to sin
with בנות מואב *Benot Moav* and the other say because you know
just a reflection on his own like lustfulness and so on. אזל
אסקיה בנגידא לפושעי ישראל Yisrael *azal askei be-negida le-poshei Yisrael*, so then
he caused now our version is the Israel sinners to be, rise
up in witchcraft, but the original גרסא girsa *girsa* is יש"ו *Yeshu*,
okay, יש"ו הנוצרי *Yeshu ha-Notzri*. So he caused Jesus to come up
in witchcraft. אמר amar, ליה *amar lei* מאן חשיב בההוא עלמא *man
chashiv be-hahu alma*, who's important in that world? I mean but you
know Jesus is sort of seen as a Jewish heretic. this context.
So who is important in that world? אמר ליה ישראל. מה לאדבוקי
בהו? Ma leidvuki behu? Should I cleave to them in this world?
אמר ליה so he gives him a very different answer than before,
טובתם דרוש רעתם לא תדרוש. tovatam drosh ra'atam lo tidrosh.
Yes, you should seek after their well-being and not after their evil,
which doesn't necessarily say you should convert, but you should try to
be good to them in this world. כל הנוגע בהן כנוגע בבבת
עינו. kol hanogea bahen kenogea bevavat eino.
If anybody tries to, you know, do something wrong to them, touch
them, it's like you're trying to poke yourself in your own eye.
אמר ליה, so he actually said, yeah, he was the one who
actually said you should be good to them in this world. דיניה
דהוא גברא במאי? dinei dehu gavra bamai?
What's that man being judged with? What's your judgment in the world
to come? אמר ליה בצואה רותחת, betzoa rotachat,
in boiling excrement. דאמר מר כל המלעיג על דברי חכמים נידון בצואה
רותחת. de'amar mar kol hamal'ig al divrei chachamim nidon betzoa rotachat.
Anybody who mocks the words of the sages is judged with boiling
excrement. So notice by the way, you know, his sin here is
being framed as like mocking the words of the sages, right? I
mean, it's much more about a Jewish heretic than somebody who is
seen as actually having, you know, attacked and oppressed and caused the,
you know, the Jews like בלעם Bilam and טיטוס. Titus. So תא
חזי ta chazi and now the גמרא Gemara comments, come and see
מה בין פושעי ישראל לנביאי אומות העולם ma bein poshei Yisrael leniviei
umot ha'olam the difference between עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. See
the difference between an Israel heretic from Israel and a prophet from
the nations who are idolaters. You know, that even in the world
to come, even after they're being these harsh judgments, the idolaters still
say you should do evil to Israel, whereas the Jewish heretics, they're
able to say no, you should actually be good to Israel. תניא
Tanya it was taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, אמר רבי אלעזר amar
Rabbi Elazar בוא וראה כמה גדול כוחה של בושה. bo u're'eh kama
gadol kocha shel busha. Now, come see how great is the power
of shame. Now, we're actually, this is a way of wrapping up
the discussion we started yesterday that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, was
destroyed because of קמצא Kamtza and בר קמצא. Bar Kamtza. So see
how great is the power of shame. שהרי סייע הקדוש ברוך הוא
את בר קמצא sheharei siya HaKadosh Baruch Hu et Bar Kamtza God
assisted בר קמצא, Bar Kamtza, right, you know, sort of it was
like obviously it was part of God's plan to destroy the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash but it all came about through, according to the
גמרא, Gemara through this story of בר קמצא Bar Kamtza and God
guided the events והחריב את ביתו ושרף את היכלו. vehachriv et beito
vesaraf et heichalo. And ultimately it caused for the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash to be destroyed and the היכל Heichal to be burnt. It's
actually interesting, right, because earlier the גמרא Gemara said because of this
rabbi who wouldn't let them do what they needed to do, זכריה
בן אבקולס Zecharya ben Avkulas החריב את בתינו ושרף את היכלנו. hechriv
et bateinu vesaraf et heichaleinu. It
was his humility. Here it is saying, right, God was the one
who destroyed His own house, right? So who are we sort of
attributing it to? It's also interesting, adding this idea of shame, that
בר קמצא Bar Kamtza was like shamed, you know, in this whole
story about these רשעים reshaim who are judged and weren't able to
even after the fact be like ashamed of what they had done,
you know, sort of and actually re-visit their actions. One also wonders
if the whole story of קמצא Kamtza and בר קמצא Bar Kamtza
is really a metaphor, not to tell you like normally it's translated
as, you know, well here it is, it's about shaming and how
terrible the sin of shaming is or sometimes it's translated in more
religious terms about שנאת חינם, sinat chinam, but it actually was a
very real-world שנאת חינם, sinat chinam, you know, as I always start
the story about the Zealots, like the fact that there were all
these factions and they were spending so much time warring against themselves,
right, and that they could have actually there was no need for
them to have actually rebelled against Rome and there was no real
need why they could not have, you know, managed to negotiate that,
not gotten into that situation to begin with and have managed to
actually survive it without the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash being destroyed. It
really was brought about because of the internal fighting and the lack
of leadership, which is the גמרא's Gemara whole story about how the
rabbis at that time, you know, were able to do something and
didn't do anything. So alright, so now the גמרא Gemara shifts, I
mean, and it really is important, I mean, to some degree maybe
that's obvious, but to another degree sometimes we get so caught up
in these stories that they become almost like, I don't know, like
fairy tales or something and you don't realize that they were real
commentary about what really brought about the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמתרנגולא ומתרנגולתא aturnegoila vetarnegoilta
on a hen and a rooster חריב טור מלכא chariv Tur Malka
this city טור מלכא Tur Malka was destroyed. So what does this
mean? דהוו נהיגי dehavu nahigi they had a practice כי הוו מפקי
חתן וכלה ki havu mapki chatan vechallah when a חתן chatan and
כלה challah would go out, meaning would, you know, be the wedding
procession, מפקי קמייהו תרנגולא ותרנגולתא. mapki kameihu tarnegoila vetarnegoilta. They would have
walk in front of them a hen and a rooster, a rooster
and a hen, excuse me, rooster and a hen. כלומר Kolomar and
which was to signify פרו ורבו כתרנגולים pru u'revu katarnegolim you should
be as fruitful as these, you know, hens and roosters. יומא חד
Yoma chad one day, I mean, you know, a hen lays an
egg on a daily basis, right? יומא חד הוה קא חליף גונדא
דרומאי. Yoma chad hava ka chalif gunda de'romai. So one day a
troop of Romans were passing through שקלינהו מינייהו shaklineihu mineihu and there
was a wedding procession but they were hungry, so they grabbed the
chickens. Okay,
so what happened? So the people נפלו עלייהו, naflu alaihu, they attacked,
they fell on them meaning they attacked them. מחונהו, makhunu, and they
hit them, they started beating up the Romans, okay, "Give us back
our chickens. This is our wedding procession." Okay, אזלו אמרו ליה לקיסר,
azlu amru lei le-keisar, so they went and they told the Caesar,
"מרדו בך יהודאי, mardu becha yehudai, the Jews are rebelling." אתא, ata,
they attacked us. אתא עלייהו, ata alaihu, so he came on them
meaning he attacked them, brought an army against them. הוה
בהו ההוא בר דרומא. havah behu hahu bar droma. Now there was
a certain man by the name of בר דרומא Bar Droma in
this Jewish village, דהוה קפיץ מילא, de-havah kafitz mila, that he could
jump a מילא, mila, okay, וקטלו בהו, ve-katlu behu, and he would
smite the Romans, he would jump a mile, I guess his sword
would be out, he'd chop them up as he would be jumping
over them. Okay, so anyway, they would not have been able to
be destroyed because he had all these superpowers. My kids like to
read this book, I don't know if anybody's heard about this, this
comic book strip called Asterix. Has anybody heard about this? It was
done by these two French Jews and it was basically about this
little village in France that there was a druid that made this
where they were able to make this magic potion that gave them
all superpowers and they were able to resist the Roman occupation during
the time of Julius Caesar. Anyway, so he said that what
inspired this—a great series, they learned a lot about Roman history by
reading it. Anyway, so he said what inspired them was the stories
about בר כוכבא Bar Kochba because if you think about it, Asterix,
right, it's spelled with an X, but Asterix is a star, right,
בר כוכבא. Bar Kochba. How the Jews were just like one small
little place that was able to resist the Romans for this long
period of time for years. Anyway, so here you have this guy
with superpowers who's able to resist the Romans. So anyway, שקליה קיסר
לתגיה, shaklei keisar le-tageih,
so the Caesar took his crown ואספיה אארעא ve-asfeh a-ara and put
it on the ground. אמר, he said, "רבוני דעלמא, ribonei de-alma, Master
of the world, כולי kulei of the entire world, אם ניחא לך,
im nicha lach, if it is in your favor, לא תמסריה לההוא
גברא לדידיה ולמלכותיה, lo timsereih le-hahu gavra le-didei u-malchuteih,
don't hand over this man meaning myself, me and my kingdom, בידיה
דחד גברא be-yadei de-chad gavra
in the hand of one man, like this will be so inappropriate
that all of Rome will be wiped out by this one Superman
here." So אכשליה פומיה, achshaleih pumeih,
so apparently his prayers were answered because אכשליה פומיה לבר דרומא. achshaleih
pumeih le-bar droma. Bar Droma's mouth tripped him up ואמר, ve-amar, and
Bar Droma said, "הלא אתה אלהים זנחתנו ולא תצא אלהים בצבאותינו." halo
atah elohim zenachtanu ve-lo tetzei elohim be-tzivotenu.
He was complaining against God even though he had these powers and
apparently he was resisting the Romans, but he said to God, "God,
You've abandoned us and You're not going out in our troops." So
because of that the Caesar was the one that sort of recognized
God and prayed to God, and Bar Droma was the one that
was complaining to God. So now before we continue with the story,
the גמרא Gemara says, "What do you mean? He was just quoting
a פסוק pasuk in תהלים." Tehillim. דוד נמי אמר הכי, David nami
amar hachi, David said that פסוק. pasuk. So דוד אתמוהי קא מתמה,
David itmuhei ka-matmei,
David was sort of saying it in wonder like, "Is it
possible that You, God, have abandoned us?" whereas Bar Droma was actually
charging God, not saying, "How is this, is it possible, it couldn't
be." He wasn't saying that; he was saying, "God, You abandoned us."
So the גמרא Gemara says,
so עלא לבית הכסא, ala be-veit ha-kisei, so what happened to בר
דרומא? Bar Droma? He went to the
bathroom. So before we had this almost comic fall of Titus and
the blown-up foot of Vespasian, so here we have this בר דרומא,
Bar Droma, this Superman, he goes to the bathroom.
אתא דרקונא, ata darkona, this serpent. Remember the דרקונא darkona that was
around the barrel of honey yesterday in the whole metaphor of ירושלים
Yerushalayim and Vespasian? So here he's going to the bathroom, came a
serpent, שמטיה לכרכשי, shamteih le-karkashei,
he basically dropped his guts, somehow he was so afraid or the
serpent bit him or something, whatever, anyway, his intestines fell out ונח
נפשיה ve-nach nafshei and he died. Okay, so he had a bathroom
accident and he died. So again, quite a sort of
comic almost, comic tragic. Anyway, אמר, so now the Caesar said, "הואיל
ואתרחיש לי ניסא," ho-il ve-itrachsh li nisa, so Caesar is very, very
פרום frum here. He said, "Since this miracle occurred to me and
God answered my prayer, הא זימנא, ha zimna, this time אשבקינהו, ishvakinhu,
I'll leave them. I won't wipe them out." So שבקינהו, shavkinhu, he
left them, ואזל אזדקר, ve-azal izdakar, and then the Jews, after Caesar
left, they got up, stood up to dance, ואכלו ושתו, ve-achalu ve-shatu,
they ate and they drank, ואדליקו שרגי, ve-adliku shragei, and they lit
candles. So it's because they were so happy that the Romans left
them, עד דאתחזי דיליונא דגושפנקא, ad de-it-chazi dilyona de-gushpanka,
until the very like the impression of a seal, a signet ring,
so like you could
בריחוק מילא be-richuk mila could be seen. There was so much light
at a mile away you could see the insignia on a signet
ring. Amar so as the Caesar was leaving and he saw all
this rejoicing he said you know מחדי חדו ביהודאי michdi chadu biyehuda'ei
the Jews are mocking me הדר אתא עליה hadar ata alei so
he turned back and he and once again you know came back
and attacked them. And now we're going to see how big was
that the city they wiped out אמר רב אסי תלת מאה אלפי
שליפי סייפא עיילו לטור מלכא amar Rav Assi tlat me'a alfi shlifai
saifa ailu l'tur malka so now obviously these numbers are grossly exaggerated
but anyway
300,000 men with drawn swords entered into טור מלכא Tur Malka וקטלו
בה תלתא יומי ותלתא לילואתא ve'katlu bah tlata yoma ve'tlata leilavata and
and you know murdered there killed there for three days and three
nights ובהך גיסא הילולי וחנגי u've'hach gisa hilulei ve'chingei so one side
of the city they were being slaughtered and on the other side
of the city somehow the word didn't get to them and they
were still
rejoicing ולא הוו ידעי הני בהני ve'lo hava yada hanei be'hanei and
they you know this half the city didn't know what was going
on in the other half of the city. I'm not exactly sure
how that's even possible or what exactly the message is but I
should stop to say that I think that the bigger message here
is first of all I think that this is true right? Didn't
the Romans like really do that with rebelling cities that they would
like completely wipe them out? The word decimate actually comes from that
period right? That doesn't mean...
actually it's from... the decimate has a different origin but the Romans
did do that.
I thought decimate was... decimate you kill every one out of every
ten or you kill...
what? No it was it was applied to Roman soldiers who were
mutinous. Oh they would order the ninety percent... nine percent... ninety percent
remaining to kill the ten percent as a way to get them
to be more cruel.
I see wow okay anyway they
they would do that the most famously they started doing that with
Carthage.
Wow right. So on the one hand obviously this would would happen
in these cities that rebelled but I actually think that the other
point about this which is often lost because normally if people are
doing this אגדתא on like תשעה באב Tisha B'Av they usually stop
before this because this isn't about the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit anymore
this is just about some city called טור מלכא. Tur Malka. But
I think the actual point of the גמרא Gemara is that you
know we so much focus on חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis that we
lose sight of the actual destruction of the way of life the
destruction of the people of the cities of the population right? There's
all the talk about the הר הבית Har HaBayit often tends to
you know... well since I was a kid anyway on תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av we tend to then include make it part of a
שואה Shoah and obviously there you know you know that's all about
the decimation of the of the population and of the people. But
in the discussions of the... and sometimes when people talk about the
שואה Shoah they say we also need to talk about the lost
culture and society and and so on. You know but anyway but
in discussions of הר הבית Har HaBayit this other part about the
human part and about not just what happened in ירושלים Yerushalayim but
what happened throughout Israel and how you know... and I think also
that makes it very poignant about how you know they have this
rooster and the hen like you know they're like this is you
know very like it's very you know sort of like you know
sort of like prosaic but it's also like these are like their
traditional practices and a certain way of life and so on and
they can't deal with the fact that you know the things are
a little bit different and the Romans are here and you have
to like just you know they couldn't even like accommodate that and
come to terms with it and then in the end it all
gets destroyed. Yes.
During the שואה Shoah Jews in one country in Eastern Europe where
the שואה Shoah didn't get to until later did not know what
was going on in neighboring countries.
No so it's similar to the idea of one half of the
city and the other half. Yes interesting. Okay
so so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
One minute. Okay. ובהך גיסא ולא הוו ידעי הני בהני. u've'hach gisa
ve'lo hava yada hanei be'hanei. בלה ה' ולא חמל bala Hashem ve'lo
chamal now we're going to quote obviously relevant פסוקים pesukim from איכה
Eicha God has swallowed up and you have not and with no
and not have compassion את כל נאות יעקב et kol ne'ot Yaakov
all of the you know cities or of יעקב. Yaakov. כי אתא
רבין אמר רבי
יוחנן אלו שיתין ריבוא עיירות ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan ailu
shitin ribo ayarot these are the sixty 600,000
excuse me sixty myriads 600,000
villages שהיו לינאי המלך בהר המלך she'hayu l'Yanai ha'melech b'har ha'melech that
ינאי Yanai had on הר המלך. Har HaMelech. I don't know how
you have 600,000 villages on one mountain. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב
אסי שיתין ריבוא עיירות d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi shitin ribo
ayarot 600,000 villages היו לינאי המלך בהר המלך hayu l'Yanai ha'melech b'har
ha'melech he had ינאי Yanai the king had this Hasmonean king וכל
אחת ואחת היו בה כיוצאי מצרים ve'chol achat ve'achat hayu bah k'yotzei
Mitzrayim and each one of those villages had as many Jews as
came out of מצרים Mitzrayim which you know was 600,000 males you
know between the ages of whatever you know twenty and up and
so on so probably about two million people per village times 600,000
you do the math.
Okay חוץ משלש שהיו בהן כפלים כיוצאי מצרים chutz mishalosh she'hayu bahen
kiflayim k'yotzei Mitzrayim
but there were three of the villages had double those that came
out of Egypt. אלו הן וכפר ביש כפר שיחליים eilu hen ve'chfar
bish kfar shichlayim these are those three villages כפר ביש Kfar Bish
כפר שיחליים. Kfar Shichlayim. and כפר Kfar דכריא. Dichraya. So what does
this mean? כפר Kfar ביש Bish means 'the bad village', דלא dela
יהבי yahavi בית beit אושפיזא, ushpiza,
that they actually were cruel, they didn't let wayfarers have a place
to sleep. כפר Kfar שיחליים Shichlayim like סדום Sedom exactly. שהיתה Shayesta
פרנסתם parnasasam מן min שיחליים, shichlayim, that they would make their living
from שיחליים, shichlayim, which is like watercress, some type of vegetable. כפר
Kfar דכריא, Dichraya, which is males, דאמר de'amar רבי Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan
שהיו shehayu נשיהם nesheihem יולדות yoldos זכרים zacharim תחילה techilla ויולדות veyoldos
נקבה nekeiva באחרונה ba'achrona ופוסקות. uposkos.
First they would have boys, then they would have girls, and then
they'd stop giving birth. So I'm not exactly sure what the point
is, like oh, once they were יוצא yotzei פרו pru ורבו? urvu?
Is this a critique that they didn't have more kids than this?
I don't know. Anyway, אמר עולא, Ulla, לדידי ledidi חזי chazi לי
ההוא hahu אתרא. asra. Now עולא Ulla said, one minute, you know,
I saw this place you're describing that you said there were six
hundred thousand villages? ואפילו ve'afilu שיתין shishin ריבותא ribusa קני kanei לא
מחזיק. machzik.
It's not even big enough for six hundred thousand reeds. How could
you say there are six hundred thousand villages? So עולא Ulla seems
to be calling them on the fact that this is a bit
of an exaggeration. So אמר ליה, but now the גמרא Gemara switches
it to be talk to be a critique from the outside. ההוא
hahu צדוקי, Tzadoki, now my guess is צדוקי, Tzadoki, I'm sure the
original גרסא girsa is מין. min. What do you have there in
the Steinsaltz? מין. min.
ההוא hahu מין, min, like
a heretic, רבי Rabbi חנינא, Chanina,
שיקו shiku משקריתו, meshakrisu, you guys are lying, right? You said it
was six hundred thousand villages and it can't even have six hundred
thousand reeds. אמר ליה, ארץ Eretz צבי Tzvi כתיב. kesiv. No, ארץ
Eretz ישראל is described as the land of the deer. מה צבי
tzvi זה, zeh, the same way a deer, אין ein עורו oro
מחזיק machzik את es בשרו, besaro, if you flay a deer, then
you would not be able to get the skin back on the
deer. So the skin itself is smaller than the body that it
contains. It stretches when it's on the body. אף af ארץ Eretz
ישראל, the same is the land of Israel, בזמן bizman שיושביה sheyoshveha
עליה, aleha,
when the people dwell in the land, רבחה, ravcha, it expands. ובזמן
ubizman שאין she'ein יושביה yoshveha עליה, aleha, when they don't dwell on
the land, גמדה, gamda, it shrinks. So that's why this place is
so small right now, but believe me, at that time it had
six hundred thousand villages, and each village had six hundred thousand people
in it. Okay. רב Rav מניומי Minyumi בר bar חלקיה Chilkiya ורב
Rav חלקיה Chilkiya בר טובייה Tuvya ורב Rav הונא Huna בר חייא
Chiya הוו havay יתבי... yasvei... anyway, but clearly though, the point is
that now we're moving from, as I said, the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. to the destruction of the population. Okay. הוו havay יתבי yasvei
גבי gabei הדדי, hadadi, these three rabbis were sitting by one another.
אמרי, amrei, and they said, איכא ika דשמיע deshamei ליה מילתא milsa
מכפר miKfar סכניא Sekanya של shel מצרים Mitzrayim לימא. leima.
If anybody heard anything about this city כפר Kfar סכניא Sekanya of
מצרים Mitzrayim let him say. Now what are we doing about מצרים?
Mitzrayim? So Sansino says, Sansino is an underused resource nowadays because the
translation is stilted and there are all these other translations, but it
has a really good footnote. And Sansino says that some surmise that
it's כפר Kfar סכניא Sekanya של shel נוצרים, Notzrim, not מצרים, Mitzrayim,
so Nazareth, and that actually apparently that was an area that later
was, you
know, rebelled not against the Romans, but sort of, you know, apparently
amongst against the Jewish populace from what I read from that footnote.
I don't know enough about that. Anyway, so here what they're trying
to do is talk about how it used to be a very
faithful place before that later... Do you know anything about that, Charlie,
about the places in... apparently there is something place called something like
כפר Kfar סכניא Sekanya in this Nazareth area. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says...
Steinsaltz says there's a city in the Galilee called סכניא.
Sekanya. What? Steinsaltz says there is a city, yeah, called סכניא. Sekanya.
Nazareth is what? A city? It's a city in Israel today. Yeah.
So I mean I think that this is probably I think this
is near that, I think it's in that area. So anyway, alright,
so if anybody heard anything about this, לימא, leima, let him say.
פתח pasach חד chad מינייהו mineihu ואמר, ve'amar, so one said, מעשה
ma'aseh בארוס be'arus וארוסה, ve'arusa,
a story about a bride and a bridegroom, or a bridegroom and
a bride, meaning it was just אירוסין, eirusin, it wasn't yet נישואין.
nisuin. So they had the קידושין kiddushin but they hadn't yet had
חופה chuppah and been married like to begin living together. שנשבו shenishbu
לבין levein העובדי ha'ovdei כוכבים, kochavim, that they were taken captive. והשיאום
vehisi'um זה zeh לזה, lazeh, and the non-Jews who presumably weren't even
aware that they had been already married. This is not sort of
like you know the whole story we say on תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av. about right the brother and the sister that they're thinking are
going to you know putting in the room the כהנים Kohanim and
they're gonna have babies and whatever they didn't realize that the brother
and sister. Anyway here actually they were already married and the non-Jews
were putting them together to make babies and to have them as
slaves. Okay, maybe they didn't, the non-Jews didn't even realize they were
married, so you should think what's the problem? So the problem is
is that they only had קידושין kiddushin and they didn't yet have
נישואין. nisuin. So that's the problem. Okay. ואמרה ve'amra לו, lo, so
she said to him, בבקשה bevakasha ממך, mimcha, she said to her
husband, please אל al תיגע tigi בי, bi, don't touch me, right
let's do we can't we can't be intimate, שאין she'ein לי כתובה
kesuva ממך. mimcha. Now what's the problem? I mean you know you're
living together, let that count as נישואין. nisuin. No the problem is
that there's no כתובה. kesuva. And you're not allowed to live together
husband and wife without a כתובה. kesuva. So ולא נגע naga בה
bah עד ad יום yom מותו. moso.
And he did not touch her till the day he died. וכשמת,
ucheshemes, and when he died, אמרה amra להן, lahen, so she said
to them, I guess the captors, ספדו sifdu לזה, lazeh, you should
eulogize this one, שקיפח shekipei את et יצרו, yitzro, he was able
to sort of be dismiss his... desires, his lusts, ויותר מיוסף veyoter
miYosef greater than Yosef. דהוה יוסף dehavah Yosef לא הוי אלא חדא
שעתא lo hava ela chada shaata Yosef only had to resist for
one moment. ודא veda and this man, my husband, כל יומא ויומא
kol yoma veyoma every day. וביוסף uveyosef לאו בחדא מיטה הוו lav
bechada mita havu
they weren't sleeping sharing a bed, והא בחדא מיטה veha bechada mita
and we were sharing a bed. וביוסף לאו אשתו uveyosef lav ishto
and
Yosef, he was resisting אשת פוטיפר eshet Potifar that wasn't his wife,
והא אשתו veha ishto and I'm his wife, but I told him
that we can't sleep together and he heeded that. פתח אידך ואמר
patach idach veamar so that was one story. Okay, so you see
how tremendously sort of righteous they were. ואמר veamar and he said,
מעשה ועמדו ארבעים מודיות בדינר. maaseh veamdu arbaim modiyot bedinar.
There was a story about this place that one time four measures
of grain cost a dinar. So grain was very cheap, okay, they
were very wealthy and very successful, grain was very cheap. נחסר השער
nechsar hashaar and then the rate went down, מודיא אחת mudya achat
that now you could only get thirty-nine measures of grain for a
dinar. So and they wanted to know why is it, what has
happened that now it's only thirty-nine measures? ובדקו ומצאו אב ובנו שבאו
על נערה מאורסה ביום הכיפורים uvadeku umatzu av uveno shebau al naara
meurasah beyom hakippurim and they found that there was a father and
son, imagine like how terrible this is, it was a father and
son doing this sin together, having sex with a betrothed woman on
Yom Kippur, and they were eating pork while they were doing it.
והביאום לבית דין וסקלום veheviyum leveit din vesakalum
and they brought them to beit din and stoned them. וחזר השער
למקומו vechazar hashaar limkomo and then the rate went back. So anyway,
they were so righteous, you know, that in general, right, that led
to how successful they were. And if there was any ever thing
that and even any sin would have derailed that, but they were
obviously very responsible for for that and they would attend to any
problems. Okay. פתח אידך ואמר patach idach veamar
another one said, מעשה באדם אחד שנתן עיניו באשתו לגרשה. maaseh beadam
echad shenatan einav beishto legaresha.
A man wanted to divorce his wife. והייתה כתובתה מרובה vehayetah ketubatah
merubah
but she had a very large ketubah. מה עשה meh asah
so what did he want to do, he wanted to get out
of having to pay her ketubah, so he wanted to basically make
it seem like it was her fault, like she had done something
to deserve to be divorced. So what did he do? הלך וזימן
את שושביניו halach veziman et shoshvinav he invited his friends, והאכילן והשקן
veheechilan vehishkan and he gave them food and he caused them to
drink, שכרן shicharan and he got them drunk, והשכיבן על מיטה אחת
vehishkivan al mita achat he had them all lie down on one
bed. והביא לובן ביצה vehevi loven beitzah
and he took the white of an egg, והטיפה ביניהן vehitipah beineihen
and he put it between them, so he made it look like
it was semen essentially. והעמיד להן עדים veheamid lahen edim and he
brought witnesses to see what had happened, almost sounds like a scene
out of Macbeth, you know. Anyway, ובא לבית דין uva leveit din
and he came to beit din and said look, these men they
must have had sex with my wife and I'm going to divorce
my, and it wasn't enough that he just did one man, he
had all these men. Anyway, והיה שם זקן אחד מתלמידי שמאי הזקן.
vehaya sham zaken echad mitalmidei Shammai hazaken. There was one man from
the descendants of the students of Shammai the elder, בבא בן בוטא
שמו. Bava ben Buta shemo. His name was Bava ben Buta. אמר
להם amar lahem and he said, כך מקובלני משמאי הזקן, kach mekubalni
miShammai hazaken, this is the tradition I have from Shammai the elder,
לובן ביצה סולד מן האור loven beitzah soled min haor if it
is an egg white, soled means it'll like shrivel up if you
apply if you put it next to fire, ושכבת זרע דוחה מן
האור veshichvat zera docha min haor
but if it were semen it would get absorbed into the cloth
if it's near fire. ובדקו ומצאו כדבריו uvadeku umatzu kidvarav and they
saw like he was right, and therefore it was an egg white
and it was not semen. והביאוהו לבית דין והלקוהו veheviuhu leveit din
vehilkuuhu and they brought this man to beit din and they gave
him lashes, והגבו כתובתה ממנו vehigbu ketubatah mimeno and they made him
pay her ketubah. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף amar leih Abaye leRav
Yosef okay, so that's how right, so it's interesting, right, because the
first story is just the righteousness of the individuals. The other story
is look, not everybody is perfect, I mean even אב ובנו שבאו
על נערה מאורסה, av uveno shebau al naara meurasah, but it's about
the responsibility they're taking in terms of their own
communal
sort of the leadership, the responsibility that the leadership is taking, the
communal righteousness and bringing them to beit din and punishing the sins,
you know, and to some degree that's in contrast to what we
saw before about not taking the full responsibility that the beit din
had. So the Gemara says, you know, for in the time of
the Beit Hamikdash. The Gemara says, אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar
leih Abaye leRav Yosef, ואחר דהוו צדיקים כולי האי. veachar dehavu tzaddikim
kulei hai. So if they were so righteous, why were they punished?
אמר ליה, משום דלא איאבלו על ירושלים. mishum delo iabalu al Yerushalayim.
So now here it's like interesting, because they did not mourn over
the destruction of Jerusalem. דכתיב, d'chtiv, שמחו את ירושלים וגילו בה כל
אוהביה שישו אתה משוש כל המתאבלים עליה. simchu et Yerushalayim vegilu vah
kol ohaveha sisu itah masos kol hamitablim aleha. So you should rejoice
with it all those who mourn for it, that only those who
share in the mourning will share in the rejoicing. And this actually
from what I understand... You know historians actually say that for certain
people like we think that the חורבן הבית was complete devastation for
everybody, all the Jews who lived in Israel. But actually for some
of those that lived not near ירושלים Yerushalayim and you know like
some of maybe the villages and so on who were quote who
were distant, you know it might not have been as you know
completely traumatic as we might have as we might imagine. So here
it understands that there could have been a village, right? And how
far is Nazareth from Jerusalem? It's in the Galilee, it's in the
Galilee, right? So the places that are very far and
that
are in the Galilee
and so on, how much did they really feel how much the
destruction of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. changed their lives? So here
you could imagine a town right that's very righteous and so on
but is like a little bit you know not feeling the communal
sense of that larger national and communal sense of the destruction of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash So again it's quite interesting right? On
the one hand they are very responsible as a community for what
goes on in their ארבע אמות, arba amos, you know within their
own village and they really take full responsibility for that but they
don't see a larger sense of a national responsibility. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says so that's story number two. Now we get
to story number three which also has to do with the destruction
of the cities and the population. אשקא דריספק Ashaka derispak based on
like a like an axle on a carriage, חריב ביתר, chariv Beitar,
ביתר Beitar was destroyed. What's that story? דהוה נהיגי Dehava nahigi that's
the practice was כי הוי מתיליד ינוקא ki avei misyalid yanuka when
a boy was born, a baby boy was born, שתלי ארזא shatlei
arza they plant a cedar tree. ינוקתא Yanukta when a baby girl
was born, שתלי תורניתא shatlei turnisa they would plant a תורניתא turnisa
which Rashi says is pines, Rashi says פין pin which I assume
means pines, is that how they translated it a pine?
Cypresses, in mine he says might be a pine but it might
be a cypress as well.
Okay okay
a cedar tree, a cedar
tree, no cedar is the boy isn't it?
Oh sorry I'm yes okay and
the girl what
do they say?
They had a pine. Pine, okay. Anyway וכי הוו מינסבי veki aveu
minsevei and when a boy and a girl would get married when
they would grow up so they would go to the boy's tree
and the girl's tree that had been planted when they were born
and קייצי להו kaitzei lo they'd cut down the trees and ועבדו
גננא ve'avdu ganana they made a חופה chuppah out of it. It's
a very beautiful מנהג. minhag. יומא חד הוי קחליפי ברתיה דקיסר Yoma
chad avei kachalfa bartei deKeisar so one day the Caesar's daughter was
passing through this town which was passing through ביתר, Beitar, איטבר אשקא
דריספק itbar ashaka derispak and the axle from her carriage broke. So
what did they do? קצו ארזא katzu arza they cut down the
most available you know the nearby cedar tree and ואייתו לה va'ayisu
lah and they brought it to her עשו aso you know to
go ahead and fix her carriage. So אתו נפלו עלייהו asu naflu
alaihu so then all the Jews of the village went and attacked
the Caesar's daughter and the and the army that was with her
because they cut down this tree, they were you know impinging on
their way of life. מחון machun they smote them they hit them
אתו אמרו ליה לקיסר asu amri leh leKeisar they came and told
the Caesar מרדו בך יהודאי mardu bach Yehuda'ei the Judeans are rebelling
against you. אתו עלייהו aso alaihu so he came against them in
war. So again the inability to appreciate you know even the slightest
adjustment to these traditional practices. Okay. גדע בחרי אף כל קרן ישראל
Gada bechori af kol keren yisrael God cut down with with fire
anger all of the horn of Israel. אמר רב זירא אמר רב
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן אלו שמונים אלף קרני מלחמה Amar rav zeira
amar rav abba amar rabi yochanan eilu shemonim elef karnei milchamah these
are eighty thousand or maybe eighty per your גרסא anyway horns of
war you know they would blow these horns when
they would come and attack.
There's a picture here a war horn, thank you. שנכנסו לכרך ביתר
Shenichnasu l'kerach beitar they came into the city of Beitar בשעה שלכדוה
besha'ah shelechduhah when they conquered it והרגו בה אנשים ונשים וטף veharghu
bah anashim venashim vetaf and they smote men women and children עד
שהלך דמן ונפל לים הגדול ad shehalach daman venaful l'yama hagadol until
the blood flowed into the Mediterranean. שמא תאמר קרובה היתה Shema tomar
kerovah hayetah the Mediterranean was nearby, no רחוקה היתה מיל rechokah hayetah
mil it was a מיל mil away or מיל mil is about
a kilometer and there was so much blood it flowed all the
way into the Mediterranean. תניא רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר שני נחלים יש
בבקעת ידים Tanya rabi eliezer hagadol omer shenei nechalim yesh bevikat yadayim
there are two wadies in בקעת ידים Bikat Yadayim which is presumably
near ביתר Beitar אחד מושך לכאן ואחד מושך לכאן echad moshech lechan
ve'echad moshech lechan one going one way and one going the other
way. And שיערו חכמים שני חלקים מים ואחד דם shiru chachamim shenei
chalakim mayim ve'echad dam and the sages estimated at that time I
assume he means that it was two-thirds water and one-third blood filled
that wady. And ומתניתא תנא vemasnisa tana and the ברייתא Braisa we
taught שבע שנים בצרו עובדי כוכבים את כרמיהם מדמן של ישראל בלא
זבל sheva shanim batzru avdei kochavim es karmeihem midaman shel yisrael belo
zevel for seven years afterwards the non-Jews harvested their their vineyards from
the blood of Israel that had seeped into the land without fertilizing
and you know I mean one cannot help but thinking about the
the land in Auschwitz right people know about how that's you know
for many you know it's very lush because of all of the
of the human you know remains that are absorbed into the land.
So אמר רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה שח
לי זקן אחד מאנשי ירושלים Amar rabi chiya bar abin amar rabi
yehoshua ben korcha sach li zakein echad mei'anshei yerushalayim Jerusalem, a certain
elder from the elders of Jerusalem whispered to me, he told me,
בבקעה זו הרג נבוזראדן רב טבחים. be'vika zu harag Nevuzaradan Rav Tabachim.
So now we're going back to the time of the first בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. In this valley Nevuzaradan, the head of the literally
butchers, you know, the head general of Nebuchadnezzar, slaughtered מאתיים ואחת עשרה
ריבוא, masayim v'achas esrei ribo, 211 myriads, which is 211 times 10,000,
which is 2.1 million. Okay, a little exaggeration. בירושלים הרג תשעים וארבע
ריבוא, bi'Yerushalayim harag tishim v'arba ribo, 94 myriads, 940,000 in Jerusalem. על
אבן אחת, al even achas, on all on one stone, עד שהלך
דמן ונגע בדמו של זכריה, ad she'halach daman v'naga b'damo shel Zechariah,
until their blood came and and touched with the blood of Zechariah.
Zechariah was a כהן Kohein that they slaughtered because he was righteous,
and יואש Yoash who was the king there saw, you know, basically
ordered him murdered. And לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayeim mah shene'emar, to fulfill
the verse it says, ודמים בדמים נגעו, v'damim b'damim naug'u, and the
blood touched against the blood. So אשכחיה, ashkechei, now this is the
famous story which actually gets worked into one of the קינות Kinot
on תשעה Tisha באב. B'Av אשכחיה לדמיה דזכריה, ashkechei l'damei d'Zechariah, so
Nevuzaradan when he entered into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. found the
blood of Zechariah. This is not the Zechariah who came back who
was one of the last נביאים Nevi'im who came back in the
time of the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash That's a different זכריה
הנביא. Zechariah HaNavi. This is the Zechariah who was a כהן Kohein
at the time of the end of the first בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash Anyway, דהוה קמרתח, de'hava kamartach, it was bubbling, it was boiling
וסליק, v'salik, you know, bubbling up. אמר, and so Nevuzaradan said מאי
האי, mai hai, what is this blood? אמרו ליה, amru lei, so
the Jews said to him דם זבחים דאישתפוך, dam zvachim d'ishtapuch, it's
a blood of sacrifices that's on the ground. אייתי דמא, ayise damma,
so he took the blood of like, you know, animals, of like
cows and sheep, ולא דמי, v'lo dami, it didn't look like it.
He knew that they were lying. אמר להו, amar lehu, אי אמריתו
לי מוטב, ei amritu li mutav, if you tell me the truth
of what this is of what this is it's good, ואי לאו,
v'ei lav, and if it's not מסריקנא לבישראייכו במסרקי דפרזלא, masrikna l'visraichu
b'masreki d'farzla, I will flay your flesh with like iron combs. אמרו
ליה, amru lei, they said to him מאי נימא לך, mai nima
lach, what should we tell you? I mean, you know, we have
to be honest with you. נביא היה בנו, navi haya banu, there
was a prophet among us דהוה קמוכח לן, de'hava kamocheach lan, and
he would, you know, he gave us מוסר, mussar, you know, he
would remonstrate us במילי דשמיא, b'milei d'shmaya, in words in the name
of God and from, you know, with heavenly words. קמינן עלויה, kaminnu
alavei, so what did we do? We didn't want to hear what
he had to say, so we rose up against him וקטלינן ליה,
v'katlinan lei, and we smashed and we killed him. והא כמה שנין,
ve'ha kamma shanin, and now it's been many years דלא קא נייח
דמיה, de'lo ka nayach damei, his blood has not stopped bubbling, you
know, has not settled. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them
אנא מפייסנא ליה, ana mefaysina lei, I will of cause I will
appease his death. אייתי סנהדרי גדולה, ayise Sanhedrin Gedolah, he took the
the large Sanhedrin וסנהדרי קטנה, v'Sanhedrin Ketana, and the smaller Sanhedrin וקטלינהו
עלויה, v'katlinhu alavei, and he slaughtered them over the blood ולא נח,
v'lo nach, and it the blood did not rest. Again gets that
issue about leadership and the responsibility on the leaders. בחורים ובתולות, bachurim
u'vesulos, then he took like innocent young young men and young women
וקטלינהו עלויה, v'katlinhu alavei, and he slaughtered them on it ולא נח,
v'lo nach, and it did not stop bubbling. אייתי תינוקות של בית
רבן, ayise tinokot shel beis rabban, and he brought the you know
the school children וקטלינהו עלויה, v'katlinhu alavei, and slaughtered them over the
blood over you know by the blood ולא נח, v'lo nach, and
it still didn't stop boiling. אמר ליה זכריה זכריה, amar lei Zechariah
Zechariah, so now Nevuzaradan said Zechariah, Zechariah טובים שבהן איבדתים, tovim she'bahen
ibadtum, I have destroyed the best among them. ניחא לך דאבדינהו לכולהו,
nicha lach d'avdinhu l'chulhu, do you want me to wipe everyone out?
כדאמר ליה הכי, k'd'amar lei hachi, so when he said this נח,
nach, then the blood stopped boiling. ובההיא שעתא, u'v'hahu sha'ata, at that
moment הרהר תשובה בדעתיה, hirher teshuvah b'da'atei, at that moment he had
a thought of תשובה teshuvah in his in his mind. אמר, and
he said ומה על נפש אחת כך, u'mah al nefesh achas kach,
if for one soul it gets seeks the vengeance like this, just
you know for for one Jewish soul ההוא גברא דקטיל כולי הני
נשמתא, hahu gavra d'katil kulei hanei nishmasa, me, I I've killed all
of these souls על אחת כמה וכמה, al achas kamma v'chamma, how
much more will I be punished for you know how greatly will
I be punished for my sins. Of course it's a little bit
funny because he was killing them because of the blood and the
blood was sort of seeking the vengeance, so anyway, but okay. Anyway,
ערק, arak, he ran away אזל, שדר שטר פטירתא לביתיה, shadar shetar
partisa l'veiseh, he sent a document to his house to sort of
distribute his property, to you know, to take care of his of
his business ואיגייר, v'isgayar, and he converted. Okay, so bet you didn't
know that. Everybody is converting. אונקלוס is converted, what was it, נירון
Niron converted, נירון Niron converted, and now נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan converted. Okay. תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, we learned in a ברייתא, Braita, נעמן, Naaman, right,
who was from that whole story with, you know, אלישע, Elisha, and
he got healed from his צרעת, tzara'at, and he basically said actually,
he said like, I will you know, I accept God and some...
I'll have to bow down to this idol because I'll go with
my master there and I won't have a choice, but basically he
had accepted God. So the גמרא Gemara. lists these ones who we
advised not to convert. בלעם Bilam said not to convert, right, and
these guys who actually did, they actually did, they actually did convert,
exactly. So נעמן גר תושב היה. Naaman ger toshav haya. נעמן Naaman
was a גר תושב, ger toshav, which means he abandoned עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. He didn't become a Jew and that's actually like פשט
in the פסוקים. psukim. נבוזראדן גר צדק הוי. Nevuzaradan ger tzedek havay.
But נבוזראדן, Nevuzaradan, he actually was a full convert. מבני בניו של
המן למדו תורה בבני ברק. Mibnei banav shel Haman lamdu Torah bi-Vnei
Brak. Now המן's Haman's grandchildren, they're still learning תורה Torah in בני
ברק, Bnei Brak, okay? מבני בניו של סיסרא לימדו תינוקות בירושלים. Mibnei
banav shel Sisra limdu tinokos bi-Yerushalayim. And the grandchildren of סיסרא, Sisra,
they're teaching school children in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So even our greatest enemies
ultimately, you know, realize the truth or their descendants find their way
into the Jewish people. מבני בניו של סנחריב, Mibnei banav shel Sancheriv,
and the, which also shows I guess the power of תשובה, teshuva,
you know, not only realizing the light and the truth even, you
know, but that actually, you know, that they're able to actually be
accepted, you know, if they do that תשובה. teshuva. The grandchildren of
סנחריב לימדו תורה ברבים, Sancheriv limdu Torah barabbim, you know, taught תורה
Torah in, you know, taught תורה Torah in public, you know, in
crowds. And who are these? So ומאן אינון שמעיה ואבטליון. U-man inun
Shmaya ve-Avtalyon. שמעיה Shmaya and אבטליון, Avtalyon, right, who were like the
leaders of the early rabbinic leaders of the Jewish people, teachers of
הלל Hillel and שמאי. Shammai. היינו דכתיב נתתי, Haynu de-ksiv nasati, okay
fine. So anyway, so pretty pretty amazing here about how all of
these like terrible people who came to destroy ישראל eventually either they
convert or children convert, they find their ways in. Actually, I think
there's a תשובה teshuva in שאלות ותשובות ממעמקים She'eilos U-Tshuvos Mi-Maamakim from
Rav Oshry's תשובה teshuva from the Holocaust where a or after the
Holocaust, like a few years after, a Nazi actually was feeling so
guilty and he wanted to actually convert to Judaism. And the question
was like would they let him convert, you know? So actually I
mean here you have a you know yeah. המן Haman was a
descendant of עמלק, Amalek, right. So it raises interesting questions about if
עמלק Amalek does תשובה teshuva can can an עמלק Amalek become a
convert? You know there's a whole רמב"ם Rambam on this and so
on, exactly. Okay. Now now wrapping up this whole point, going back
to the זכריה Zecharya story. היינו דכתיב נתתי את דמיך על צחיח
סלע לבלתי הכסות. Haynu de-ksiv nasati es damayich al tzhiach sela levilti
hikasos. I put the blood on the flint on the you know
on the flat of the rock that it could not be covered
over. So the blood would not get absorbed, it was on the
floor of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. and that's that פסוק pasuk
that evokes that, you know, connects to that idea. Okay. הקול קול
יעקב והידים ידי עשו. Ha-kol kol Yaakov ve-ha-yadayim yedei Esav. The voice
is the voice of יעקב Yaakov and the hands are the hands
of עשו, Esav, which raises like interesting questions, right? To some degree,
it continues a theme about how these, you know, these people that
have, you know, destroyed and oppressed and killed, you know, amongst the
Jews, the if you would the עשו Esav model has become part
of יעקב, Yaakov, right? So this intersection of קול יעקב kol Yaakov
and ידים ידי עשו. yadayim yedei Esav. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with this. הקול זה אדריאנוס Ha-kol ze Adryanus קיסר, Keisar,
which was was I mean so much of the you know martyrs
of the עשרה הרוגי מלכות asara harugei malchus was under Hadrian. שהרג
באלכסנדריא של מצרים ששים רבוא על ששים רבוא. She-harag be-Alexandrya shel Mitzrayim
shishim ribo al shishim ribo. He killed in Alexandria of Egypt 600,000
times 600,000. So what is that? I can't even do the math.
360 million or something, more maybe, I don't know. Anyway, okay. כפלים
כיוצאי מצרים. Kiflayim k-yotzei Mitzrayim. Double, well, unless it means 600,000 plus
not times, and then it's because that seems like it anyway, double
those that went Egypt. So what does that mean that הקול קול
יעקב? ha-kol kol Yaakov? So so so רש"י Rashi says, let's see
what that means. הכל צוחה ובכי עולה מיעקב. Ha-kol tzevacha u-vechi ola
mi-Yaakov. Okay, so קול קול יעקב kol kol Yaakov here means that
the sound, the outcry, the wailing comes from יעקב Yaakov because of
ידים ידי עשו. yadayim yedei Esav. That's how it's being read. קול
יעקב, kol Yaakov, so then there's another interpretation. Or הקול, ha-kol, that's
the sound of wailing that comes from that's the slaughter of Hadrian.
קול יעקב זה אספסיאנוס Aspasyanus קיסר, Keisar, Vespasian, שהרג בכרך ביתר ארבע
מאות רבוא, she-harag bi-krach Beitar arba me'os ribo, 400 myriad, which would
be 4 million if you're doing the math. ואמרי לה ארבעת אלפים
רבוא, Ve-amri lah arba'as alafim ribo, 4000 myriad, which is 40 million.
Okay, so again, the outcry from because of ידים ידי עשו, yadayim
yedei Esav, you know, the קול יעקב kol Yaakov here is the
outcry, the wailing. והידים ידי עשו זו מלכות הרשעה. Ve-ha-yadayim yedei Esav
zu malchus ha-resha'a. This is the evil kingdom, meaning Rome, שהחריבה את
ביתנו ושרפה את היכלנו והגליתנו מארצנו. she-hachriva es beisenu ve-sarfa es heichalenu
ve-higlisenu me-artzenu. So again, that's a repeating theme. So first we had
that it was because of the humility of this what was his
name, of this rabbi, and then it was because of בושה busha
that God caused הגליתנו מארצנו. higlisenu me-artzenu. Now it's Rome that הגלינו
מארצנו, higlianu meartzeinu, right? So who's to blame? Is it, that was
ר' זכריה, Reb Zechariah, that's right, that was another זכריה. Zechariah. That
was interesting. Anyway, so anyway, is it like the failure of leadership
that caused it? Is it the way that people acted against one
another that caused it, right? Is it God that caused it? Is
it the Romans that caused it? It's very interesting the same phrase
being attributed to different actors throughout these אגדתות. Agadotas. Okay, דבר אחר,
Davar acher, קול קול יעקב, Kol kol Yaakov, אין לך תפילה, ein
lecha tefilla, this is the more דרוש drush I think we're more
familiar with with קול יעקב. Kol Yaakov. You don't have a prayer
שמועלת shemoelet that works, that's effective, שאין בו מזרעו של יעקב. she'ein
bo mizaro shel Yaakov. So now we're getting the intersection that we
had sort of עשו Esav converting into יעקב, Yaakov, and now we're
saying any prayer that God hears somehow has some influence from the
Jewish people. I don't exactly know how, if it's being prayed by
Nazarenes, but okay. Maybe. Anyway, והידיים ידי עשו, Vehayadayim yedei Esav, the
hands are hands of Esav, אין לך מלחמה ein lecha milchama that
נוצחת, notzachat, and you don't have any war that is successful שאין
בו מזרעו של עשו, she'ein bo mizaro shel Esav, that somehow there's
not somebody involved in it that is from the descendants of עשו.
Esav. היינו דאמר ר' אלעזר, Heinu de'amar Reb Elazar, בשוט לשון תחבא,
beshot lashon techavei, in the sort of the slander of the tongue
shall be hidden, בחרחורי לשון תחבא, bechirchurei lashon techavei, with somehow the
contentiousness or again the slander of the tongue, it will be hidden.
It's not exactly clear how it's why he says the fighting of
the tongue. Anyway, רש"י Rashi says this is going back to the
idea of the לשון הרע. lashon hara. So I guess tying back
to what do you call it, about the about קמצא ובר קמצא,
Kamtza u'Var Kamtza, that it came through but through in-fighting that that
ultimately led to the destruction. Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, Mai d'chtiv, על נהרות בבל, Al
naharot Bavel, שם ישבנו גם בכינו בזכרנו את ציון, sham yashavnu gam
bachinu bezochrenu et Tziyon, going back to the time of the Babylonians.
מלמד שהראה הקדוש ברוך הוא לדוד, Melamed she'hera HaKadosh Baruch Hu leDavid,
so this is understood to have been written by דוד, David, although
it's understood to well by דוד, David, some things are clearly earlier,
but the גמרא doesn't want to attribute something to something later. So
anyway, so God showed דוד, David, חורבן בית ראשון וחורבן בית שני,
churban bayit rishon vechurban bayit sheni, both destructions. חורבן בית ראשון, Churban
bayit rishon, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, על נהרות בבל, Al naharot Bavel, Babylon, שם
ישבנו גם בכינו. sham yashavnu gam bachinu. בית שני, Bayit sheni, דכתיב,
זכור ה' לבני אדום את יום ירושלים האומרים ערו ערו עד היסוד
בה. Zechor Hashem livnei Edom et yom Yerushalayim ha'omrim aru aru ad
hayesod bah. Remember God the children of אדום, Edom, the day of
Jerusalem when they said, destroy, destroy until the very until the very
foundation. So they were after the בית Beis המקדש Hamikdash destroyed. So
rather than interpreting it to be the literal בני אדום bnei Edom
that were near in a neighboring country, it's reading it as the
figurative אדום Edom of Rome in the second בית המקדש. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, ואיתימא ר' אמי, ve'iteima
Reb Ami, ורמי ליה ממתניתא תנא. u'rami lei mimatnita tana. מעשה בארבע
מאות ילדים ומאות ילדות, Maaseh be'arba me'ot yeladim ume'ot yeladot, famous story,
400 boys and girls, שנשבו לקלון, shenishbu lekalon, that they were being
taken for shame, which basically means that they were going to be
taken for not just for slaves but for sexual purposes. They were
taken into captivity by the Romans. הרגישו בעצמם למה הן מתבקשים, Hirgishu
be'atzmam lema hen mitbakshim, they had a sense of why they were
being taken captive. אמרו Imru and they said, אם אנו טובעים בים
אנו באים לחיי העולם הבא? Im anu tovim bayam anu baim lechayei
ha'olam haba? So if a question mark, meaning if we were to
drown ourselves in the sea, would we get the world to come?
דרש להן הגדול שבהן, Darash lahen hagadol shebahen, so the eldest one
interpreted the following verse. אמר ה' מבשן אשיב אשיב ממצולות ים, Amar
Hashem mibashan ashiv ashiv mimtzulot yam, from the Bashan I will return
I will bring back from the depths of the sea. מבשן אשיב,
Mibashan ashiv, what does that mean? מבין שיני אריות אשיב, mibein shinei
arayot ashiv, from the teeth of the lions I will return them.
ממצולות ים, Mimtzulot yam, אלו שטבועים בים, elu shetvuim bayam, those that
drown themselves in the sea. I'm not exactly getting the שיני אריות
shinei arayot unless if that means like Rome. Anyway, if you go
to save yourself from the Romans by drowning yourself in the sea,
God says I will bring you back. כיון ששמעו ילדות כך, Keivan
sheshamu yeladot kach, when the girls heard this, קפצו כולן ונפלו לתוך
הים, kafzu kulan venaflo letoch hayam, they jumped into the sea and
drowned themselves. נשאו ילדים קל וחומר בעצמן, Nas'u yeladim kal vachomer be'atzman,
the boys made a קל וחומר kal vachomer about themselves. ואמרו ומה
הללו שדרכן לכך, Ve'amru uma halalu shedarkan lekach, they that at least
it's man raping a woman but it's anyway it's that at least
something that's more I guess that type of sex is seen as
more common, כך אנו כך, kach anu kach, and they were willing
to jump into the ocean. אנו שאין דרכנו לכך, Anu she'ein darkenu
lekach, we who are going to be raped by men, that's even
less natural, על אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kama vechama, how much
more so should we go ahead and do this? אף הן קפצו
לתוך הים, Af hen kafzu letoch hayam, they jumped into the ocean,
ועליהם הכתוב אומר, ve'aleihem hakatuv omer, by them the verse says, כי
עליך הורגנו כל היום נחשבנו כצאן טבחה. Ki alecha horagnu kol hayom
nechshavnu ketzon tivcha. So for you we were slaughtered the whole day
we've been like sheep to the slaughter. Now this actually is a
very important מדרש midrash because it was used by תוספות Tosafot and
the חכמי אשכנז chachmei Ashkenaz in terms of this whole issue about
are you allowed to take your life in order to save self
from, this happened in the time of the crusades, from a fear
of forced conversion, right? Or is it יהרג ואל יעבור Yehareg ve'al
ya'avor that you can give up your life if the non-Jew is
going to say that they're going to kill you? But if they're
not going to kill you and they're just going to force you
to convert, can you actively take your own life? Can תורה Torah
actually condone, הלכה Halacha condone suicide or taking your own life in
order to save yourself from, well, in the time of תוספות Tosafot
it was baptism, but here it's actually from sexual sin, okay, and
is that permissible or not? So חיים סולובייצ'יק Haym Soloveitchik wrote this
whole article that there's no halakhic basis for it and תוספות Tosafot
had it post-facto justify it and the proof that it's not really
halakhically justified is that they draw on מדרשים Midrashim and there we
all know that מדרשים Midrashim are not actually legitimate as part of
the halakhic discourse. There's like a lot of assumptions in that argument.
I mean, but he starts by the presumption that מדרשים Midrashim are
not, it's true that they're not a normal part of the halakhic
discourse, but nevertheless they express rabbinic values. You cannot read this מדרש
Midrash without getting a sense that the חז"ל Chazal are saying that
they think that this was the right thing
to
do. So whether it's
strictly a halakhic text
or not, in
terms of an
attitude of do we
actually think that this was a
right activity, maybe
not a mandated one but a
praiseworthy
one, I don't think you can
read
it otherwise. Yes. I
know I didn't read
the article carefully, but my,
I saw him saying that
it was unusual
for תוספות Tosafot to do that, to
draw. That it
showed תוספות. Tosafot. No, actually, yeah,
but I
think he was making a
bigger point. First
of
all, תוספות Tosafot does
it a good deal, I mean,
but his point
was that it's not a
standard halakhic
move to do that. And
the funny
thing is that
again,
even if you don't admit, concede
that
it's not a halakhic text, it doesn't
directly, it's
not a direct
part
of the halakhic
discourse,
you can't
read this
אגדתא without thinking that
it says something
about חז"ל Chazal's attitude to
this phenomenon, right?
And if you know
what חז"ל Chazal's attitude to this
phenomenon is, how could
that
not influence the way you
read other halakhic
texts?
Even if you're not
considering
this a halakhic
text itself.
So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafot,
קפצו כולם ונפלו
לתוך הים, Kaptzu kulam venaflo letoch hayam, he says,
and in מסכת
עבודה זרה,
Masechet Avodah Zarah,
מוטב
שייטלה
מי שנתנה ואל יחבל
בעצמו, Mutav she-yitla mi she-netana ve-al yachabel be-atzmo, which is the
countertext, right, about
the רבי חנינא בן
תרדיון Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon that
was put out, the
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, better God should take my soul
and I
shouldn't do injury to myself.
הכי יראים היו מיסורים, Hachi yere'im hayu mi-yisurim, דאמרינן, de-amrinan, אלמלא
נגדו לחנניה מישאל ועזריה פלחו לצלמא. ilmale nigdu le-Chananya Mishael ve-Azarya palchu
le-tzalma. They were
afraid
of being tortured and afflictions, because
it's one thing if
you know you're going
to be killed
and you're
going
to be able to say fine,
kill
me, right, I'll just take the death.
But if
you're going to be
tortured and you're afraid
you're going
to succumb to
the torture, then you're
going
to in the end wind
up doing the
sin. So this is
the only way out of the
sin is by taking
your own life. Okay?
And had they tortured
חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Chananya Mishael ve-Azarya, they
would have worshipped
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. ועוד על כורחם
היו מענים אותם ולא היו
הורגים
אותם כלל.
Ve-od al korcham hayu
meanim otam velo hayu
horgim otam klal. And
anyway, they could have raped them
without killing
them. So if the
only way to escape, it's fine to say
give up your
life if that's the
choice being given
to you, but if
your only way to escape
the sin
is by taking your own life,
then תוספות
Tosafot is
saying,
well, then
at least it seems that
that's at least an
acceptable course of
action. At least
that's how what תוספות
Tosafot learns from
this גמרא. So it's
a very actually important גמרא in
that larger conversation. So we'll
actually see
another story just like this when we
continue
tomorrow.